<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://alex.mulatinho.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://alex.mulatinho.net/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-09-30T22:19:46-03:00</updated><id>http://alex.mulatinho.net/</id><title type="html">Alexandre Mulatinho</title><subtitle>A blog about linux, open source, development and the life of an software engineer ;)</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Two years of remote working: What I learned</title><link href="http://alex.mulatinho.net/2017/07/27/two-years-of-remote-working-what-i-learned.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Two years of remote working: What I learned" /><published>2017-07-27T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2017-07-27T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://alex.mulatinho.net/2017/07/27/two-years-of-remote-working-what-i-learned</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://alex.mulatinho.net/2017/07/27/two-years-of-remote-working-what-i-learned.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://mulatinho.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/img_20170322_140523390.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_20170322_140523390&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this month I completed exactly two years of remote working, what adventure! To remind me about this in future and also to share with you all I resolve to write about that here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FEAR&lt;/strong&gt;, that was the first emotion that I felt when I decide to abandon my last physical work where I was in job for at least 5 (five) years. I was not happy at all but only who pass for something like that knows what I am talking about,
it is not easy to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do I have all the skills to make a change?
Would I get the same status of my work in another company?
Would I have the same stability in another company?
And if I lose my job after the change?
And if I don’t achieve do the new job that I will be contracted?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FREEDOM&lt;/strong&gt;, was the first feeling that I felt when I subjugate all those doubts. Why we have so much fear of changes? After reading some books I thought about this for a lot of time and it seems to me that is something that we acquire after youthness, at school we are taught so hard that we need something stable, something to catch us, that we forget about how importantly if sometimes we take risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ohh, the changes! In these two years my whole life changed a lot! I had my first kid, my marriage get even better, my financial life is growing exponencial because now I have the time to study and make investments in market, and I just have to thanks God for all that. I always ask myself: “and if I wouldnt change ten years ago? and if I wouldnt change my last job five years ago too? Would I had the same happiness that I have now?”. Changes are important, you have to make a move sometimes, you need to take risks. You need to make mistakes but you have to fix your life before get old and frustrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean, I already worked for about 15 (fiveteen) years. So I know how is lose a job, unjustly and justly. It is a type of change too but you don’t decide about that at least almost every time. So I had a sensation of freedom when I choice to quit my stable job to a new adventure that would test my skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing that almost everyone asks me when I say that I work in my home is: “How is to work at home? Seems pretty awesome!” and I always answer at this with “Indeed, it is, but it is not too easy as you think.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You have to be organized.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You have to motivate yourself everyday.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You have to adapt to changes in your company.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You need to be sociable with the people you work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You NEED to document all you do and log your hours and your work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And principally, you need to organize your life: do some exercises, organize your food and separate your free time from your job time. Don’t be mad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be warned, If you work remote and other people don’t, some changes will happen and sometimes they will forget to consult you, you need to adapt. Some people, like any other job, will had envy or just will try to turn things dificult for you, you have to adapt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be &lt;strong&gt;trustable&lt;/strong&gt;, be &lt;strong&gt;productive&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;strong&gt;Don’t bother&lt;/strong&gt; yourself with &lt;strong&gt;little things&lt;/strong&gt;. Instead, be clever. Work on &lt;strong&gt;solutions&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;be the solutions&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do a little half of that perhaps you enjoy working remotely too. Otherwise probably you will get disappointed and be the same you was when you decide change, a person with a lot of fears hidden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you need a change too? Do your soul claims for that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start now&lt;/strong&gt;, put the things you need to do in a paper and after some time, be the change!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="life" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">DevOps: Ansible Basics</title><link href="http://alex.mulatinho.net/2017/01/27/devops-ansible-basics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="DevOps: Ansible Basics" /><published>2017-01-27T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2017-01-27T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://alex.mulatinho.net/2017/01/27/devops-ansible-basics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://alex.mulatinho.net/2017/01/27/devops-ansible-basics.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.ansible.com&quot;&gt;Ansible&lt;/a&gt; is one of the best tools in DevOps that I like, he just need a simply configuration and can help you with a lot of tasks in your day by day on your infrastructure, today I will show to you how to configure him to work with a lot of servers and how to automate some simple tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;advantages-of-ansible&quot;&gt;Advantages of Ansible&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Easy to use and fast response&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Highly configurable to almost every task you need to do&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SSH based, just use &lt;strong&gt;ssh-keygen, ssh-copy-id&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;ssh-add&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Free software sponsored by Red Hat&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Playbooks to make complex tasks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-how-we-begin-use-this-tool&quot;&gt;So how we begin use this tool?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very first thing you need to do is obviously install Ansible on your system. You can do this by typing on linux&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# yum install ansible # (redhat)
# apt-get install ansible # (debian/ubuntu)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or on your OSX:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ /usr/bin/ruby -e &quot;$(curl -fsSL \
https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Homebrew/install/master/install)&quot;
$ brew install ansible
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-inventory-file&quot;&gt;The inventory file&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ansible needs a file to specify all servers you want to control, you can use a tag name to make an group  to all servers you want by category, below we set two groups: &lt;strong&gt;appservers&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;databases&lt;/strong&gt;, note that you don’t need to specify one by one in a line, you can use regex to simplify (this is awesome!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[appservers]
staging1.dev.yourcompany.com
staging2.dev.yourcompany.com
staging3.dev.yourcompany.com

[databases]
db[1:5].dev.yourcompany.com
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, or perhaps before that, as told before Ansible needs a SSH master key that need to be added on &lt;strong&gt;/.ssh/authorize_keys&lt;/strong&gt; file into each of your slave servers, to do that you just need to proceed like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ssh-keygen -t rsa # (to generate your key, enter until finish)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you will get a &lt;strong&gt;~/.ssh/id_rsa.pub&lt;/strong&gt; public key file in your &lt;strong&gt;$HOME&lt;/strong&gt; directory; So now you need to distribute your public-key to all servers you need control, this can be easy if you have only ten servers to administer or a pain if you have to do this in more than 100+ servers, so here’s a tip:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a file with all your servers like this:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;  root@server1.dev.company.com
  root@server2.dev.company.com
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;(I will not show to you how to make this with inventory file as input, but you can!)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Use this command-line to copy your keys to each server and insert root-password&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;  $ while read LINE; do ssh-copy-id $LINE; done &amp;lt; /tmp/servers
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using Ansible in command-line&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All set? So lets try do something really cool here. This is the most basic syntax of ansible:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$ ansible :target: -i inventory-file :actions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where &lt;strong&gt;:target:&lt;/strong&gt; is the group of servers in your inventory file or just an string &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; to contemplate all servers in your inventory, the &lt;strong&gt;:actions:&lt;/strong&gt; can be a simply command like below or a more complex command-line using ansible modules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;get-all-kernel-versions-of-our-servers&quot;&gt;Get all kernel versions of our servers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$ ansible all -i yourcompany.conf -u root -a “uname -a”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;staging1.dev.yourcompany.com | SUCCESS | rc=0 &amp;gt;&amp;gt;
Linux staging1.dev 3.13.0-92-generic #139-Ubuntu SMP Tue Jun 28 20:42:26 UTC 2016 x86_64 x86_64 x86_64 GNU/Linux

staging3.dev.yourcompany.com | SUCCESS | rc=0 &amp;gt;&amp;gt;
Linux staging3.dev 3.13.0-92-generic #139-Ubuntu SMP Tue Jun 28 20:42:26 UTC 2016 x86_64 x86_64 x86_64 GNU/Linux

db2.dev.yourcompany.com | SUCCESS | rc=0 &amp;gt;&amp;gt;
Linux db2.dev 3.13.0-92-generic #139-Ubuntu SMP Tue Jun 28 20:42:26 UTC 2016 x86_64 x86_64 x86_64 GNU/Linux

staging2.dev.yourcompany.com | SUCCESS | rc=0 &amp;gt;&amp;gt;
Linux staging2.dev.yourcompany.com 3.13.0-92-generic #139-Ubuntu SMP Tue Jun 28 20:42:26 UTC 2016 x86_64 x86_64 x86_64 GNU/Linux
(Note that all servers responded with your kernel)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;use-a-default-module-ping-to-check-if-databasesare-alive&quot;&gt;Use a default module &lt;strong&gt;ping&lt;/strong&gt; to check if databases are alive&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$ ansible databases -i yourcompany.conf -m ping&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;db1.dev.yourcompany.com | SUCCESS =&amp;gt; {
    &quot;changed&quot;: false,
    &quot;ping&quot;: &quot;pong&quot;
}
db2.dev.yourcompany.com | SUCCESS =&amp;gt; {
    &quot;changed&quot;: false,
    &quot;ping&quot;: &quot;pong&quot;
}
....
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;use-a-default-module-apt-to-install-a-mysql-database&quot;&gt;Use a default module &lt;strong&gt;apt&lt;/strong&gt; to install a mysql database&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$ ansible databases -i yourcompany.conf \
-m apt -a “name=mysql-server state=latest”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-how-can-i-know-what-modules-are-available&quot;&gt;So how can I know what modules are available?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are listed here -&amp;gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.ansible.com/ansible/list_of_all_modules.html&quot;&gt;http://docs.ansible.com/ansible/list_of_all_modules.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;playbooks-the-real-thing&quot;&gt;Playbooks: The real thing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, now you know that you can send commands and use modules to process in all your servers with just one command line, thats cool! But what really amazing in Ansible are the playbooks! A playbook is just a file with a template engine called &lt;a href=&quot;http://yaml.org&quot;&gt;YAML&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://jinja.pocoo.org/docs/2.9/templates/#builtin-filters&quot;&gt;Jinja&lt;/a&gt; to apply some filters, variables and others, with that you can do a lot of automate complex tasks in your servers. Lets take a look into a sample file called ‘&lt;strong&gt;install_apache.yml&lt;/strong&gt;’:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;---
- hosts: appservers
  vars:
    http_port: 80
    max_clients: 200
  remote_user: root
  tasks:
  - name: install or upgrade apache to latest version
    yum: name=httpd state=latest
  - name: write the apache config file
    template: src=./httpd.j2 dest=/etc/httpd.conf
    notify:
    - restart apache
  - name: ensure apache is running (and enable it at boot)
    service: name=httpd state=started enabled=yes
  handlers:
    - name: restart apache
      service: name=httpd state=restarted
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;hosts&lt;/strong&gt; -&amp;gt; means that all these tasks will only be executed in the group defined after the word, here
&lt;strong&gt;appservers,&lt;/strong&gt; defined by our inventory file in the begin of this post.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;vars&lt;/strong&gt; -&amp;gt; are variables you define to process tasks with it, note that variables are defined line by line.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;remote_user&lt;/strong&gt; -&amp;gt; another way to use &lt;strong&gt;-u root&lt;/strong&gt; without need to put in cmd.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;name&lt;/strong&gt; -&amp;gt; is just a name you define to implement a task&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;template&lt;/strong&gt; -&amp;gt; in this case is just a way to say, copy my source file defined as ./httpd.j2 to destination server on /etc/httpd.conf&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;notify&lt;/strong&gt; -&amp;gt; is a tag that call a job (&lt;strong&gt;restart apache&lt;/strong&gt;) in handlers block at the end of execution of the current block&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, to resume this playbook will:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Install the latest version of httpd apache on all your &lt;strong&gt;appservers&lt;/strong&gt;
*Copy your local &lt;strong&gt;httpd.j2&lt;/strong&gt; file to remote server on &lt;strong&gt;/etc/httpd.conf&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put your variables where you set in &lt;strong&gt;httpd.j2&lt;/strong&gt; file&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Restart apache after that&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set apache to run automatically after a boot/reboot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you see you can do a lot with this, without this you would need to enter in each server and make these tasks one by one without any human mistake, with ansible you just need to type this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$ ansible-playbook -i yourcompany.conf install_apache.yml&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On next time we will show to you how to do more complex examples, best practices and directory structure to help on your day tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thats it for now! What are you waiting for? Use ansible to automate your tasks now!! :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="artigos" /><category term="devops" /><category term="sysadm" /><summary type="html">Ansible is one of the best tools in DevOps that I like, he just need a simply configuration and can help you with a lot of tasks in your day by day on your infrastructure, today I will show to you how to configure him to work with a lot of servers and how to automate some simple tasks.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to upload to Amazon S3 using REST</title><link href="http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/10/26/how-to-upload-to-amazon-s3-using-rest.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to upload to Amazon S3 using REST" /><published>2016-10-26T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2016-10-26T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/10/26/how-to-upload-to-amazon-s3-using-rest</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/10/26/how-to-upload-to-amazon-s3-using-rest.html">&lt;p&gt;Hello friends!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look on the internet a alternative way to upload files on Amazon S3 without &lt;strong&gt;AWS-SDK&lt;/strong&gt; and then you will know that is a dificult thing for many; Wait a second, why someone will need to use S3 without the Amazon SDK? That’s the problem! We all know that sometimes you can’t do simple a import/require in some lib written by another guy/girl to turn things to into a easy way. That’s the beauty of an challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to win that, all you need to do is read two docs of Amazon:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/API/RESTObjectPUT.html&quot;&gt;http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/API/RESTObjectPUT.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.aws.amazon.com/general/latest/gr/signature-version-4.html&quot;&gt;http://docs.aws.amazon.com/general/latest/gr/signature-version-4.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first documentation describes how you handle the HTTP PUT using simple REST and the second describes how to implements the Amazon signature based on &lt;strong&gt;AWS_ACCESS_KEY&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;AWS_SECRET_KEY&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Backing to the problem, days ago in my work we need to face this problem: the development version of a framework that we use can’t import AWS-SDK into project and after the mess that this problem caused, it make me think in do this post on blog;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was already do it a year ago using shell-script when I need to automatize a build process of MacOS to send the .IPA into S3, so I start to do some changes in code and finally written two new version: one in shell script and other in node.js; The principal problem found, the root of many problems to some guys is the signature process, as described on Amazon docs all you need to sign is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;HTTP-RESOURCE
MD5_BASE64_HASH
mimetype
DateInIsoUTCTime
someHeadersOfAmazon
fullPathOfObjectFile
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HTTP-RESOURCE&lt;/strong&gt; is just the HTTP REQUEST TYPE: PUT/GET..&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MD5_BASE64_HASH&lt;/strong&gt; is one of the tricks of Amazon Doc (bad trick)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;mimetype&lt;/strong&gt; i just use &lt;strong&gt;application/octet-stream&lt;/strong&gt; works for all types of file&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DateInIsoUTCTime&lt;/strong&gt; like -&amp;gt; Wed, 26 Oct 2016 12:09:45 +0000&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;someHeadersOfAmazon&lt;/strong&gt; extra header of Amazon that you need to pass&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;fullPathOfObjectFile&lt;/strong&gt; /yourBucketName/dir1/subdir2/yourFile.jpg&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or in resume:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;PUT
YUORQaKyyJWlorHlFqBtCQ==
application/octet-stream
Fri, 25 Nov 2016 14:27:42 +0000
x-amz-acl:public-read
/2e8dae9c-aad2-4d10-8abc-a7e24d80b4af/darwinorigins.jpg
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pay attention here, If you type one character byte wrong then your signature will receive the error below when you try to send your file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;Error&amp;gt;&amp;lt;Code&amp;gt;SignatureDoesNotMatch&amp;lt;/Code&amp;gt;&amp;lt;Message&amp;gt;The request signature we calculated does not match the signature you provided. Check your key and signing method.&amp;lt;/Message&amp;gt;&amp;lt;AWSAccessKeyId&amp;gt;AKIAIJ5QILNVUULONEGQ&amp;lt;/AWSAccessKeyId&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, later I will post more details here if someone needs and also the node.js code using just the builtin libs: crypto, fs, https and buffer; until then that’s the cURL version&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/mulatinho/cf148b96248ad5d1d49e8fd84c982454.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the node.JS version, using just native modules;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/mulatinho/28e01801d92d3d0000e7935d854b9fd8.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope it helps someone! :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="artigos" /><category term="bash" /><category term="programming" /><summary type="html">Hello friends!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Back! - The Tao of Programming</title><link href="http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/10/13/the-tao-of-programming.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Back! - The Tao of Programming" /><published>2016-10-13T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2016-10-13T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/10/13/the-tao-of-programming</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/10/13/the-tao-of-programming.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://mulatinho.files.wordpress.com/2016/10/taoofprogramming.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;taoofprogramming&quot; /&gt;I’m back from holidays! And with a new job! :D Still working remote now with something that I like more, Linux and software development! Just a little change: now its for web! When I get things okay here I will continue write some articles here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now just a good quote from a book that I recommend: 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Tao-Programming-Geoffrey-James/dp/0931137071&quot;&gt;The Tao of Programming&lt;/a&gt;. I hope you get a copy and have a good read!Price Wang’s programmer was coding software. His fingers danced upon the keyboard. The program compiled without an error message, and the program ran like a gentle wind. Excellent!” the Price exclaimed, “Your technique is faultless!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Technique?” said the programmer, turning from his terminal, “What I follow is the Tao – beyond all technique. When I first began to program I would see before me the whole program in one mass. After three years I no longer saw this mass. Instead, I used subroutines. But now I  see nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My whole being exists in a formless void. My senses are idle. My spirit, free to work without a plan, follows its own instinct. In short, my program writes itself. True, sometimes there are difficult problems. I see them coming, I slow down, I watch silently. Then I change a single line of code and the difficulties vanish like puffs of idle smoke. I then compile the program. I sit still and let the joy of the work fill my being. I close myeyes for a moment and then log off.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Price Wang said, “Would that all of my programmers were as wise!”
– Geoffrey James, “The Tao of Programming”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="life" /><category term="references" /><summary type="html">I’m back from holidays! And with a new job! :D Still working remote now with something that I like more, Linux and software development! Just a little change: now its for web! When I get things okay here I will continue write some articles here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Upgrade your #Slackware #Linux to (i486|x86_64) -current version</title><link href="http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/08/25/upgrade-your-slackware-linux-to-i486x86_64-current-version.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Upgrade your #Slackware #Linux to (i486|x86_64) -current version" /><published>2016-08-25T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2016-08-25T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/08/25/upgrade-your-slackware-linux-to-i486x86_64-current-version</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/08/25/upgrade-your-slackware-linux-to-i486x86_64-current-version.html">&lt;p&gt;Hello friends!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today is 2016/08/25, &lt;strong&gt;25 years of Linux&lt;/strong&gt;! Happy Birthday!! :D :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we gonna talk about how to upgrade a Slackware, we will use just the official slackware package management tool (&lt;strong&gt;slackpkg&lt;/strong&gt;), lets upgrade a slackware 14.2 to a -current for example (this also works with other versions too, but try upgrade to the next always or deal with consequences).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is &lt;strong&gt;slackpkg&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slackpkg is a system package management tool developed by PiterPunk and oficially supported by Slackware, some of the most common subcommands are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;slackpkg update          -&amp;gt; synchronize with your mirror 
slackpkg search package  -&amp;gt; looks for 'package' into mirror
slackpkg install package -&amp;gt; install 'package' from mirror
slackpkg upgrade package -&amp;gt; upgrade 'package' from mirror
slackpkg upgrade-all     -&amp;gt; upgrade all packages installed
slackpkg install-new     -&amp;gt; install new software available in repository
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First&lt;/strong&gt;, install and &lt;strong&gt;upgrade&lt;/strong&gt; your &lt;strong&gt;slackpkg&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# slackpkg update  #(choose a mirror in /etc/slackpkg/mirrors)
# slackpkg upgrade slackpkg
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the TDS Mirror but you can choice any -current mirror you like there. Then add the kernel packages into blacklist (&lt;strong&gt;/etc/slackpkg/blacklist&lt;/strong&gt;) make sure that looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#kernel-firmware
#kernel-generic
#kernel-generic-smp
#kernel-headers
#kernel-huge
#kernel-huge-smp
#kernel-modules
#kernel-modules-smp
#kernel-source
(this is not totally necessary but I like to upgrade kernels after upgrade all other softwares)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Second&lt;/strong&gt;, then upgrade your glibc-solibs, this is EXTREMELY NECESSARY to not crash your system after some upgrades of software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# slackpkg upgrade glibc-solibs
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Third&lt;/strong&gt;, install and upgrade all your new software&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# slackpkg install-new
# slackpkg upgrade-all
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kernel&quot;&gt;Kernel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you dont build your kernel youself, uncomment lines of blacklist (&lt;strong&gt;/etc/slackpkg/blacklist&lt;/strong&gt;) to build the new kernel of Slackware repository. Check your lilo.conf or grub and apply the new kernel if you like (take care here, confirm that a new kernel was installed and check the images)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# cp /boot/vmlinuz /boot/vmlinuz-backup
# sed -i '/#kernel/s/^#//g' /etc/slackpkg/blacklist
# slackpkg upgrade-all 
# vim /etc/lilo.conf
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;huge.s&lt;/strong&gt; Slackware default kernel (built-in) have a lot of issues when we need use some softwares that require some modules/built-in by default, an example is the Docker. (huge.s default slackware kernel doesn’t support Docker very good). So you can choose use the &lt;strong&gt;generic kernel&lt;/strong&gt; that has almost any module to load after boot the kernel, solving some of these issues. If you choose to do that, type the commands below, if you dont know what are you doing skip this part and use default &lt;strong&gt;/boot/vmlinuz&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# /usr/share/mkinitrd/mkinitrd_command_generator.sh
mkinitrd -c -k 4.4.16 -f ext4 -r /dev/sda1 -m xhci-pci:ohci-pci:ehci-pci:xhci-hcd:uhci-hcd:ehci-hcd:hid:usbhid:i2c-hid:hid_generic:hid-cherry:hid-logitech:hid-logitech-dj:hid-logitech-hidpp:hid-lenovo:hid-microsoft:hid_multitouch:jbd2:mbcache:ext4 -u -o /boot/initrd.gz
(this will generate this command to build a initrd.gz image, run this)
(it also, of course, creates '/boot/initrd.gz' with your def modules)
# vim /etc/lilo.conf # or your grub. i dont use this
(put your initrd image here and choice a vmlinuz-generic as default image)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your lilo.conf should now look like this (&lt;strong&gt;tip&lt;/strong&gt;: create another entry with old kernel, so if this fail to boot you can boot with the older)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;image = /boot/vmlinuz-generic  # re-check if you use vmlinuz
 root = /dev/sda1              # change if not your root disk
 initrd = /boot/initrd.gz
 label = Slack64-Generic
 read-only
image = /boot/vmlinuz-backup
 root = /dev/sda1
 label = Slack64-Okay
 read-only
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then save your MBR and reboot your system!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# lilo -v  (check this with attention)
# reboot
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And welcome to the &lt;strong&gt;-current&lt;/strong&gt; version of Slackware, keep it upgraded :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="linux" /><category term="slackware" /><summary type="html">Hello friends!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Installing Libvirt / QEMU for KVM Virtualization on #Slackware</title><link href="http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/08/25/installing-libvirt-qemu-for-kvm-virtualization-on-slackware.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Installing Libvirt / QEMU for KVM Virtualization on #Slackware" /><published>2016-08-25T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2016-08-25T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/08/25/installing-libvirt-qemu-for-kvm-virtualization-on-slackware</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/08/25/installing-libvirt-qemu-for-kvm-virtualization-on-slackware.html">&lt;p&gt;Hello friends!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today is 2016/08/25, 
&lt;strong&gt;25 years of Linux&lt;/strong&gt;
! Happy Birthday!! :D :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we gonna talk about how to install 
&lt;strong&gt;Libvirt and QEMU&lt;/strong&gt;
 to use 
&lt;strong&gt;KVM&lt;/strong&gt;
 Virtualization systems. To do that you can use many strategies here we will use just the official slackware package management tool (
&lt;strong&gt;slackpkg&lt;/strong&gt;
) and some of “unofficial” scripts from Slackbuilds (if you dont know how to use and install Slackbuilds please see the post 
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://alex.mulatinho.net/2014/11/13/how-i-build-almost-every-package-in-my-slackware-linux/&quot;&gt;How I build and install almost every package in my slackware linux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
) to install Libvirt.###First, dont forget to enable your Virtualization in BIOS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some BIOS come to the user with the Virtualization disabled by default, to check in your Linux if you has the support for virtualization just type this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$ egrep –color ‘(vmx|smx)’ /proc/cpuinfo
If you doesn’t see any ouput then 
&lt;strong&gt;you need to enable Virtualization in BIOS&lt;/strong&gt;
! If you can’t find any “Virtualization” there then perhaps you don’t have Virtualization support in your CPU :(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;#&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Installing Libvirt to use KVM virtualization&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download the lastest slackbuids scripts and then go to libvirt and build&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;git-clone-gitslackbuildsorgslackbuildsgit&quot;&gt;git clone git://slackbuilds.org/slackbuilds.git&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;cd-slackbuildslibrarieslibvirt&quot;&gt;cd slackbuilds/libraries/libvirt&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;source-info-wget--c-download-sh-slackbuild&quot;&gt;source *info; wget -c $DOWNLOAD; sh *SlackBuild&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic packages for you mount your virtualization server are 
&lt;strong&gt;libvirt&lt;/strong&gt;
 and 
&lt;strong&gt;qemu&lt;/strong&gt;
 but for a graphical manager you could also install the 
&lt;strong&gt;virt-manager&lt;/strong&gt;
 software, this script helps you build all that you need to get these packages in 
&lt;strong&gt;.t?z&lt;/strong&gt;
 format and install with 
&lt;strong&gt;installpkg&lt;/strong&gt;
.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I don’t know how you choice your packages, so if you see something like this during the build of Libvirt, this is what you need to do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*error #1 (first try this)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;configure: error: You must install the pciaccess module to build with udev
Don’t panic! Just browse the official packages with slackpkg like that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;slackpkg-search-pciaccess&quot;&gt;slackpkg search pciaccess&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[uninstalled] - libpciaccess-0.13.4-x86_61-1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;slackpkg-install-libpciaccess&quot;&gt;slackpkg install libpciaccess&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*error #2 (second, try the slackbuild)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;configure: error: You must install the libyajl library &amp;amp; headers to compile libvirt
No panic again! Just install the dependencies and repeat the process until there is no other package&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;find-slackbuilds--iname-yajl&quot;&gt;find ~/slackbuilds -iname ‘&lt;em&gt;yajl&lt;/em&gt;’&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;/root/slackbuilds/libraries/yajl&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;cd-slackbuildslibrariesyajl&quot;&gt;cd ~/slackbuilds/libraries/yajl&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;source-info-wget--c-download-sh-slackbuild-1&quot;&gt;source *info; wget -c $DOWNLOAD; sh *SlackBuild&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;installpkg-tmpyajl&quot;&gt;installpkg /tmp/yajl*&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And done! If you install all the dependencies you should now have a 
&lt;strong&gt;libvirt&lt;em&gt;.txz**
 and 
**qemu&lt;/em&gt;t?z&lt;/strong&gt;
 packages into your
&lt;strong&gt;/tmp&lt;/strong&gt;
 directory and you just need to install they using 
&lt;strong&gt;installpkg&lt;/strong&gt;
.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Starting your Libvirt daemon to run your VM guests&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slackware still uses runlevels scripts into 
&lt;strong&gt;/etc/rc.d&lt;/strong&gt;
 directory so to start libvirt you need to do&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;sh-etcrcdrclibvirt-start&quot;&gt;sh /etc/rc.d/rc.libvirt start&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting virtlockd: /usr/sbin/virtlockd -d
Starting virtlogd: /usr/sbin/virtlogd -d
Starting libvirtd: /usr/sbin/libvirtd -d
To enable this in boot&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;chmod-ux-etcrcdrclibvirt&quot;&gt;chmod u+x /etc/rc.d/rc.libvirt&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;echo-etcrcdrclibvirt-start-etcrcdrclocal&quot;&gt;echo ‘/etc/rc.d/rc.libvirt start’ » /etc/rc.d/rc.local&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See my slackware VM guest in action&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;virsh-list&quot;&gt;virsh list&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Id Name State
—————————————————-
 1 slack64-srv01 running
And that’s it for now! Wait for my new article soon: 
&lt;strong&gt;KVM Virtualization with command line. &lt;/strong&gt;
Hope you enjoy it! :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="linux" /><category term="slackware" /><category term="virtualization" /><summary type="html">Hello friends!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Desafio Shell Script 001</title><link href="http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/08/17/desafio-shell-script-001.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Desafio Shell Script 001" /><published>2016-08-17T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2016-08-17T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/08/17/desafio-shell-script-001</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/08/17/desafio-shell-script-001.html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;layout: post
title: ‘Desafio Shell Script #001’
tags:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bash&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;challenges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;programming&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;script
—Dona Fernanda resolveu casar-se com Carlos, o padre porém disse que os noivos não poderiam escolher a data de casamento devido a grande quantidade de solicitações na igreja. Vários noivos também estavam ansiosos para saber quando poderiam se casar naquela linda igreja, para dizer a cada casal o dia exato em que eles poderiam se casar o padre solicitou que eles fornecessem de 1 até 5 dias no mês de sua preferência e desenvolveu um algoritmo que ajudaria a resolver este impasse de forma aleatória e justa agora e no futuro, ele definiu:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*T&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;quantidade de casamentos na fila&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*M&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mês do casamento&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*N&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;quantidade de dias do mês disponível&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*Vx&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Valor do dia na posição X (V1, V2, V3…)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###&lt;strong&gt;ENTRADA VÁLIDA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TN V1 V2 V3 … VxM&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cada linha corresponde a uma entrada do casal, então se 
&lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;
 for igual 
&lt;strong&gt;10&lt;/strong&gt;
, existiriam 10 casais para casar na igreja em determinado mês, e por consequência, haveriam 10 linhas de entrada informando os dias preferidos do casal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###&lt;strong&gt;POR EXEMPLO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;55 2 7 5 8 145 2 4 14 8 151 403 2 7 92&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###&lt;strong&gt;RESTRIÇÕES&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;T &amp;gt; 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; T &amp;lt;= 20M &amp;gt; 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; M &amp;lt;= 12N &amp;gt; 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; N &amp;lt;= 5V &amp;gt; 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; V &amp;lt; 32 &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*O dia a ser escolhido deve ser o 
&lt;strong&gt;menor do grupo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Caso um casal tenha selecionado um dia já escolhido por outro ele ficará com o próximo dia possível, se houver (por exemplo, 
&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;
 = 4 = { 1, 3, 4, 6 } se os dias 
&lt;strong&gt;1, 3 e 4&lt;/strong&gt;
 já tiverem sido escolhidos, o casal poderá tentar o próximo item, o quarto número, o dia 
&lt;strong&gt;6&lt;/strong&gt;
), 
&lt;strong&gt;mas precisa ser sempre o menor número do grupo&lt;/strong&gt;
.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Em caso de não haver outro dia disponível para o casal deverá ser escrito:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*“O casal número 
&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;
 só pode casar no próximo mês pois já tem um casal nos dias selecionados”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Em caso de violação de restrição deverá ser escrito&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*“Padre, foi encontrado uma inconsistência nos dados.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###&lt;strong&gt;RESPOSTA VÁLIDA / SAÍDA VÁLIDA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Padre, são 5 Casamentos em FevereiroO casal número 1 ficou de casar no dia 2 de FevereiroO casal número 2 ficou de casar no dia 4 de FevereiroO casal número 3 só pode casar no próximo mês pois já tem um casal nos dias selecionadosPadre, foi encontrado uma inconsistência nos dados.O casal número 5 ficou de casar no dia 7 de Fevereiro&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###&lt;strong&gt;EXPLICAÇÃO DA SAÍDA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Padre, são 5 casamentos em Fevereiro”&lt;/strong&gt;
 é o número 
&lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;
 de casamentos de entrada e o mês 
&lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt;
 da entrada&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“O casal número 1 ficou de casar no dia 2 de Fevereiro”&lt;/strong&gt;
é o primeiro casal que tem os dias N = {2, 7, 5, 8, 14} disponíveis e o menor possível é o dia 2 de Fevereiro&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“O casal número 2 ficou de casar no dia 4 de Fevereiro”&lt;/strong&gt;
 é o segundo casal que tem os dias N = {2, 4, 14, 8, 15} disponíveise o menor possível é o dia 4 de Fevereiro&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“O casal número 3 só pode casar no próximo mês pois já tem um casal nos dias selecionados”&lt;/strong&gt;
é o terceiro casal que tem os dias N = {4} disponíveis mas como já existia um casal com o dia 4, não é possível realizar o casamento&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Padre, foi encontrado uma inconsistência nos dados do casal 4.  :(“&lt;/strong&gt;
é a mensagem de erro em caso de violação de restrição&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“O casal número 5 ficou de casar no dia 7 de Fevereiro”&lt;/strong&gt;
é o quinto casal que tem os dias N = {2 7 9} disponíveis e o menor possível é o dia 7 de Fevereiro&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###MAIS TESTES PARA VALIDAÇÃO&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gerador de testes aleatórios válidos&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;bash$ ( T=$(( (RANDOM % 20) + 1 )); echo $T; \
for i in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;seq 1 $T&lt;/code&gt;; \
do N=$(( (RANDOM % 5) + 1 )) ; echo -n “$N “; \
for x in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;seq 1 $N&lt;/code&gt;; do V=$(( (RANDOM % 31) + 1)); echo -n “$V “; done; \
echo; done; echo $(( (RANDOM % 12) +1 )) )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teste #01&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;55 21 26 4 1 155 19 11 7 16 171 284 29 6 21 251 115&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teste #02&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;33 28 26 72 29 163 8 14 154&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teste #03&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;53 17 31 161 151 74 31 30 12 12 20 273&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teste #04&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;181 213 23 24 55 15 11 19 28 85 11 9 16 16 51 41 44 4 8 7 264 23 12 11 281 72 28 273 27 13 313 30 29 115 2 5 10 20 145 4 16 5 17 252 3 202 17 25 19 21 2 24 255 16 8 18 23 285&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teste #05&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;115 7 19 30 2 223 8 23 305 25 4 16 17 313 18 31 143 6 3 192 20 12 27 222 16 194 9 28 18 212 10 202 29 97
Quer ver a minha versão com entradas e saídas funcionando??&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pastebin.com/VvbxBZWD&quot;&gt;http://pastebin.com/VvbxBZWD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conseguiu resolver? Poste suas respostas nos comentários! Quer saber a solução? Entre em contato comigo ou procure na lista de Shell-Script a thread “Desafio Shell-Script #001 do Mulato” ;-)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">layout: post title: ‘Desafio Shell Script #001’ tags: bash challenges programming script —Dona Fernanda resolveu casar-se com Carlos, o padre porém disse que os noivos não poderiam escolher a data de casamento devido a grande quantidade de solicitações na igreja. Vários noivos também estavam ansiosos para saber quando poderiam se casar naquela linda igreja, para dizer a cada casal o dia exato em que eles poderiam se casar o padre solicitou que eles fornecessem de 1 até 5 dias no mês de sua preferência e desenvolveu um algoritmo que ajudaria a resolver este impasse de forma aleatória e justa agora e no futuro, ele definiu:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bash Financeiro na Bolsa</title><link href="http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/08/11/bash-financeiro-na-bolsa.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bash Financeiro na Bolsa" /><published>2016-08-11T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2016-08-11T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/08/11/bash-financeiro-na-bolsa</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/08/11/bash-financeiro-na-bolsa.html">&lt;p&gt;bom, eu diariamente utilizo os cálculos listados neste artigo para poder realizar os meus próprios investimentos, por isso achei que poderia ser útil para alguém, pretendo atualizar com mais no futuro; existe bilhões de pessoas neste mundo e cada um tem um jeito de realizar suas tarefas, meus cálculos geralmente são feitos utilizando a shell BASH em vez de uma calculadora comum. (p.s. valores abaixo sem citar impostos de day-trade, corretagem e emolumentos)&lt;em&gt;**&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*ALGUMAS OPERAÇÕES SIMPLES USANDO O BC&lt;/strong&gt;
O comando 
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gnu.org/software/bc/manual/html_mono/bc.html&quot;&gt;bc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
 é uma calculadora poderosa que pode rodar na linha de comando simplesmente fornecendo de entrada uma conta matemática&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$ echo 4.26-2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;bc2.26&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vejamos algumas operações simples de matemática no bc&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$ echo ‘scale=2;(5.15+4)/2’&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;bc  # scale=2 mostra apenas 2 decimais4.57$ echo ‘2^16’&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;bc                # 2 elevado a 16&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;65536$ echo ‘(8+2)-(17-7)’&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;bc &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vejamos algumas operações úteis de percentagem que podem até ser usadas pra calcular rendimento ou simplesmente para a sua análise diária&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$ echo 4.26*0.1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;bc  # 10% de 4.26.42$ echo 4.26*0.25&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;bc # 25% de 4.261.06$ echo 4.26*1.05&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;bc # 5% a mais de 4.264.47$ echo 4.26*1.25&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;bc # 25% a mais de 4.265.32$ echo 3.25*0.84&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;bc # 3.25 desvalorizou 16% (1.00 - 0.16 = 0.84)2.73&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*CÁLCULOS QUE UTILIZO A OPERAR NO MERCADO DE AÇÕES &lt;/strong&gt;
calcular o custo de compra de um ativo (ação) no mercado de ações, neste exemplo 
&lt;strong&gt;800&lt;/strong&gt;
 papéis da 
&lt;strong&gt;USIM3&lt;/strong&gt;
 (
&lt;strong&gt;R$ 8,40&lt;/strong&gt;
 na data do artigo)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$ echo ‘800*8.4’&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;bc&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6720.0
e se depois de alguns dias decidir vender os papéis; calcular o lucro na venda de um ativo, suponha que o 
&lt;strong&gt;USIM3&lt;/strong&gt;
 em alguns dias vá para 
&lt;strong&gt;R$ 8,75&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$ echo ‘(800&lt;em&gt;8.75)-(800&lt;/em&gt;8.4)’&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;bc&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;280.00
note que o rendimento é relacionado a quantidade de ações e do valor do papel, vamos ver mais alguns exemplos: agora suponha que antes da ação subir ela caiu para 
&lt;strong&gt;R$ 8,28&lt;/strong&gt;
 e após análise decidimos comprar mais 
&lt;strong&gt;400&lt;/strong&gt;
 papéis da 
&lt;strong&gt;USIM3&lt;/strong&gt;
 acreditando que este ativo vai subir em breve. agora seguindo as regras da BMFBOVESPA é necessário calcular o preço médio do papel após os dois investimentos:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*USIM3 (R$ 8,40) X 800 papéis = R$ 6.720,00&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*USIM3 (R$ 8,28) X 400 papéis = R$ 3.312,00&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*Total de papéis é igual a 1200 (800 + 400)&lt;/strong&gt;
fazendo o cálculo final para obter a média de compra&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$ echo ‘scale=2;((400&lt;em&gt;8.28)+(800&lt;/em&gt;8.4))/1200’|bc
8.36
e o lucro na venda, supondo que o valor dos papéis volte a atingir 
&lt;strong&gt;R$ 8,75&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$ echo ‘(1200&lt;em&gt;8.75)-(1200&lt;/em&gt;8.36)’|bc
468.00
yeah! um rendimento líquido de 
&lt;strong&gt;R$ 468,00&lt;/strong&gt;
 menos as taxas de corretagem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*CÁLCULOS QUE UTILIZO A OPERAR NO MERCADO DE TESOURO DIRETO &lt;/strong&gt;
calcular o rendimento médio por mês baseado na SELIC (
&lt;strong&gt;14,25%&lt;/strong&gt;
 na data do artigo);&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$ echo ‘scale=2; 14.25/12’&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;bc&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.18
ou seja, o rendimento mensal médio é de 
&lt;strong&gt;1.18%&lt;/strong&gt;
, o dobro do rendimento da poupança que na data deste artigo está por volta de 
&lt;strong&gt;6%&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;agora um cálculo simples de juros compostos, onde as variáveis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*initial&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;representa o valor inicial investido;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*interest&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a taxa de rendimento médio mensal;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*months&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;o número de meses em que o investimento será realizado;
bastando trocar os valores abaixo você consegue resultados como:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$ initial=50000; interest=1.018; months=48; \
for i in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;seq 1 $months&lt;/code&gt;; do \
initial=&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;echo &quot;scale=2; $initial * $interest&quot;|bc&lt;/code&gt;; \
printf “month %2d, r$ %12.2f\n” $i $initial; done
https://gist.github.com/mulatinho/a4c8ee4b5a0d6162e32834b371085394&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uma ótima ferramenta que utilizo para ver gráficos, mais uma vez acho que não é tão adequado pra day-trade porque tem delay de minutos, é o 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tradingview.com&quot;&gt;Trading View&lt;/a&gt; que é free e perfeito na minha opinião, várias ferramentas e indicadores úteis para você tomar as melhores decisões; Aqui vai uns screenshots:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[gallery ids=”1276,1279” type=”slideshow”]&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">bom, eu diariamente utilizo os cálculos listados neste artigo para poder realizar os meus próprios investimentos, por isso achei que poderia ser útil para alguém, pretendo atualizar com mais no futuro; existe bilhões de pessoas neste mundo e cada um tem um jeito de realizar suas tarefas, meus cálculos geralmente são feitos utilizando a shell BASH em vez de uma calculadora comum. (p.s. valores abaixo sem citar impostos de day-trade, corretagem e emolumentos)**</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Avaliacao E Gerenciamento De Riscos</title><link href="http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/08/09/avaliacao-e-gerenciamento-de-riscos.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Avaliacao E Gerenciamento De Riscos" /><published>2016-08-09T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2016-08-09T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/08/09/avaliacao-e-gerenciamento-de-riscos</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/08/09/avaliacao-e-gerenciamento-de-riscos.html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;layout: post
title: Avaliação e Gerenciamento de Riscos
tags:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;security
—##Parte I: Avaliação de Riscos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olá, este post faz parte de uma sequência de artigos sobre 
&lt;strong&gt;segurança da informação&lt;/strong&gt;
, resolvi fazê-los tanto para ajudar os interessados no tema como para fixar alguns pontos na minha cabeça, além é claro, de poder deixar como consulta em algum lugar no blog. Antes de mais nada, eu não sou o dono da verdade, então muita coisa escrita aqui pode ser feita de formas diferentes para se atingir objetivos diferentes, aqui eu mostro coisas que eu aplico no meu dia ou que já apliquei em empresas anteriores;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Conheces teu inimigo e conhece-te a ti mesmo; se tiveres cem combates a travar, cem vezes serás vitorioso. Se ignoras teu inimigo e conheces a ti mesmo, tuas chances de perder e de ganhar serão idênticas. Se ignoras ao mesmo tempo teu inimigo e a ti mesmo, só contarás teus combates por tuas derrotas. - Sun Tzu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O nosso primeiro tema será 
&lt;strong&gt;avaliação e gerenciamento de riscos&lt;/strong&gt;
, um tema base para a disciplina de segurança da informação; Você pode estar lendo sobre isso pela primeira vez mas saiba que as grandes empresas do Brasil e do mundo utilizam esta prática já há bastante tempo; com base nesse contexto veremos como classificar o risco, para isso a primeira coisa que devemos definir é o significado do risco.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Um dos padrões e documentos mais referenciados e utilizados em segurança da informação e principalmente nesta disciplina de avaliação de riscos é o NIST 800-30 [1] que é considerado um MUST READ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Então, o que é risco?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Risco, em segurança da informação, se trata de toda a ameaça em que uma organização esteja ou possa estar envolvida, todo o evento que se concretizado cause problemas ao negócio, imagem ou funcionamento da empresa; Como analista de segurança da informação um dos principais trabalhos que você tem que desenvolver é identificar que ameaças podem atingir uma organização e quais medidas você deve tomar em caso de acontecimento de um evento.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O risco pode ser divido entre muitas formas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Físicos: Servidores expostos fisicamente para funcionários,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Lógicos: Uma porta aberta em um servidor, uma rede mal segmentada,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Naturais: Enchente, furacão, raios,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Imprevisíveis: No-break quebrado, queda de energia municipal;
Enfim, quase 
&lt;strong&gt;qualquer coisa que afete o funcionamento do seu negócio&lt;/strong&gt;
; acho que este é o ponto principal, para que sua empresa dê lucro ou desempenhe sua atividade de forma eficiente ela deve se livrar dos riscos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Implementação&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Segundo Vaughan [2], os passos que devem ser seguidos para que possa existir um bom plano para avaliação e gerenciamento de riscos são:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Determinar quais os principais objetivos a se atingir;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Identificar os riscos aos quais a organização está exposta;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Avaliar estes riscos de forma criteriosa;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Considerar as alternativas e selecionar dispositivos para o tratamento dos riscos;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Implementar as decisões tomadas;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Avaliar e revisar o processo continuamente;
Identificar quais os riscos que a sua organização está exposta não é uma tarefa fácil, exige disciplina e discernimento mas também muitas horas de conversas com 
&lt;strong&gt;os principais envolvidos&lt;/strong&gt;
 no funcionamento da empresa, isso quase sempre (note o quase) é feito conversando com os gerentes das áreas da empresa;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dica do Mulato #01&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marque reuniões com todos os gerentes da empresa;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peça para que na opinião deles informem o que deve ser protegido;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aceite informações de outras áreas mas peça que se concentrem nas suas;
E principalmente, você deve estar atento aos riscos que envolvem 
&lt;strong&gt;o modelo de negócio da empresa&lt;/strong&gt;
 e os riscos envolvidos com sua 
&lt;strong&gt;infra-estrutura de negócio.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dica do Mulato #02&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Estude o segmento da empresa;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conheça seus concorrentes e procure entender os riscos do negócio;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Procure conhecer o máximo possível a infra estrutura da empresa;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Classificação do Risco&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uma das formas mais eficientes e recomendadas para se avaliar os riscos depois de listá-los é fornecer os pesos corretos para cada risco em forma de severidade (impacto que o evento causará na empresa caso aconteça) e a probabilidade de o evento  acontecer, neste caso faremos isso desta forma:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Severidade (para o negócio)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chance/Probabilidade de acontecer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*1-2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Pouquíssima severidade;&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*3-4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Impacto baixo para empresa;&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*5-6&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Impacto moderado;&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*7-8&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;Sérios problemas caso ocorra;&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*9-10&lt;/strong&gt;
: Desastroso para empresa;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*2:&lt;/strong&gt;
 Risco
&lt;strong&gt; baixo&lt;/strong&gt;
;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*5:&lt;/strong&gt;
 Risco 
&lt;strong&gt;médio&lt;/strong&gt;
;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*10:&lt;/strong&gt;
 Risco 
&lt;strong&gt;alto&lt;/strong&gt;
;
Para calcular o risco geral simplesmente multiplicamos os dois valores:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&amp;gt; Risco Geral = Severidade X Probabilidade/Chance
E é gerado um valor quantitativo até 100 informando o risco geral do evento. Esta é a tabela que utilizo mas você pode modificar para qualquer outro tipo de qualificação: 
quantitativa ou qualitativa, desde que no final os riscos sejam expostos e as decisões possam ser tomadas de forma mais eficiente e com foco na sua 
&lt;strong&gt;importância&lt;/strong&gt;
 e 
&lt;strong&gt;ocorrência&lt;/strong&gt;
;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A partir deste momento já é possível preparar a nossa primeira tabela de apoio a decisões! Para 
&lt;strong&gt;servir de exemplo&lt;/strong&gt;
, suponha que a empresa que estamos analisando é uma startup de desenvolvimento web com escritório físico onde trabalham 5 funcionários e existem 2 servidores DELL onde um é ativo e o outro fica de contingência com poucos serviços, a empresa fica localizada dentro de uma casa em um bairro bem seguro mas onde já houve antes registros de enchentes em sua área, e toda sua infra-estrutura esta localizada fisicamente na casa, no entanto eles possuem uma cópia de backups diários e assets importantes da empresa em um servidor dedicado na internet;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digamos que após conversar com o dono da empresa e o responsável técnico da equipe de funcionários eles levantaram pra gente que os principais riscos que eles consideram são:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*“Não temos muita orientação em segurança no processo de desenvolvimento”,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*“As vezes recebemos clientes que acessam a rede privada da empresa”,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*“Não temos uma política muito bem definida de backup, mandamos pra nuvem”,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*“As vezes temos queda de energia municipal e duramos pouco tempo sem energia”,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*“Não temos fornecedores de confiança, não temos segurança física”
Após uma análise inicial decidimos identificar os 10 principais riscos:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risco / Descrição&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impacto&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risco Geral&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enchente que pode danificar equipamentos&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baixa&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;14&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Invasão ao local físico, furto&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baixa&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;16&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ausência de Suporte/Fornecedor de Equipamentos de Hardware (Servidor, Máquinas, Equip. de Rede) *&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Média&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;25&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acesso indevido a rede privada empresa *&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Média&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;30&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Invasão Local (Física) ao Servidor da Empresa (Cliente / Funcionário mal intencionado / Estranho) *&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Média&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;35&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problemas/Perda de Backups da Empresa&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Média&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;40&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Queda de energia municipal/ausência de no-break&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Média&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;40&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ausência de treinamento e medidas de segurança voltadas ao desenvolvimento WEB&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Média&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;45&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ataques a páginas hospedadas no servidor (CSRF, SQL/Param Injection, Session Hijacking, etc)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alta&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;70&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Invasão ao servidor principal com acesso administrativo&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alta&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;90
Veremos que essa tabela irá crescer no próximo artigo quando falarmos em como gerenciar estes riscos e como aplicar os controles adequados, ira notar-se também que alguns itens irão receber resposta imediata afim de reduzir a sua chance ou o seu impacto (*);&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Cálculo do Risco&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Um dos conceitos mais importantes que um analista de segurança da informação deve compreender e difundir entre os principais interessados é o 
&lt;strong&gt;cálculo do risco&lt;/strong&gt;
, para isso foram definidos três variáveis que te ajudam a chegar ao custo do risco para uma empresa, são elas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*ARO&lt;/strong&gt;
 (Annualized Rate of Ocurrence/Possibilidade de Ocorrência no Ano), percentagem da possibilidade ocorrência do evento em um ano;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*ALE&lt;/strong&gt;
 (Annual Loss Expectancy/Expectativa de Perda Anual), expectativa de perda anual em valores monetários de um evento/risco específico;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*SLE&lt;/strong&gt;
 (Single Loss Expectancy/Expecativa de Perda Única), valores em moeda que representam o custo total caso um evento aconteça; Este valor pode ser subdivido entre dois itens:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*AV&lt;/strong&gt;
 (Asset Value/Valor do Ativo)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*EF&lt;/strong&gt;
 (Exposure Factor/Fator de Exposição)
O que nos leva as seguintes fórmulas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&amp;gt;  AV x EF  = SLE
  -&amp;gt; SLE x ARO = ALE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exemplo #01:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suponha que a página que mais dá dinheiro a essa empresa rende foi avaliada em 
&lt;strong&gt;R$ 26.000,00&lt;/strong&gt;
 e após a reunião em conjunto com os envolvidos foi descoberto que o site já passou por um processo de auditoria de segurança e que está bem padronizado há alguns anos, então foi definido um fato de exposição (
&lt;strong&gt;EF&lt;/strong&gt;
) de 
&lt;strong&gt;25%&lt;/strong&gt;
, então nosso 
&lt;strong&gt;SLE&lt;/strong&gt;
 aqui é R$ 26.000,00 x 0.25 = 
&lt;strong&gt;R$ 6.500,00&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exemplo #02:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digamos que o servidor físico que hospeda as páginas web rende por hora 
&lt;strong&gt;R$ 200,00&lt;/strong&gt;
 em horários de pico a empresa, a probabilidade de acontecer  uma falha no hardware neste ano é de 
&lt;strong&gt;20%&lt;/strong&gt;
 ou 
&lt;strong&gt;1 em 5&lt;/strong&gt;
, caso ocorra a falha será necessário a compra de mais um equipamento de contingência no valor de 
&lt;strong&gt;R$ 6.000&lt;/strong&gt;
, mais o tempo de manutenção necessário para voltar ao ar sem problemas, que da ultima vez foi estimado em 
&lt;strong&gt;4 horas&lt;/strong&gt;
;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neste exemplo o 
&lt;strong&gt;ARO&lt;/strong&gt;
 é 0.20 e o 
&lt;strong&gt;SLE&lt;/strong&gt;
 é R$ 6.800,00 (R$ 200 x 4 horas + R$6.000 servidor), então usando a fórmula acima qual é o ALE (Expectativa de Perda Anual)?  O 
&lt;strong&gt;ALE&lt;/strong&gt;
 é R$ 1.360,00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Então, é isso! Nós vimos aqui a primeira parte do post 
Avaliação e Gerenciamento de Riscos, com o conhecimento daqui: 
&lt;strong&gt;classificação&lt;/strong&gt;
 e 
&lt;strong&gt;cálculo do risco&lt;/strong&gt;
, conseguiremos a informação necessária para gerenciar os riscos afim de mitigá-los ou extinguí-los quando possível, de forma organizada e orientada a um processo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###&lt;strong&gt;Referências&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/nistpubs/800-30/sp800-30.pdf&quot;&gt;NIST 800-30 - Risk Management Guide for Information Technology Systems&lt;/a&gt;[2] Fundamentals of Risk and Insurance, Vaughan and Vaughan&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">layout: post title: Avaliação e Gerenciamento de Riscos tags: security —##Parte I: Avaliação de Riscos</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Validate fields and other objects in #Swift #iOS</title><link href="http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/03/15/validate-fields-and-other-objects-in-swift-ios.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Validate fields and other objects in #Swift #iOS" /><published>2016-03-15T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2016-03-15T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/03/15/validate-fields-and-other-objects-in-swift-ios</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://alex.mulatinho.net/2016/03/15/validate-fields-and-other-objects-in-swift-ios.html">&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately we all know that we can’t put everything what we are working in, on a simple blog, I have to understand this since years ago when I worked at some government department. But I can show what I am doing now just for fun and for registry to me in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;we were had some problems here, especially when we’d need to try validate a lot of forms that involved things like UITextField, UISegmentedControl, etc. To solve this issue I had to create one class with methods like:.insert(object, checkType, labelError, errorMessage) // magic goes here.
.showErrors() // print on screen all erros like below
.count() // return the quantity of erros below
.result() // return if all tests are passed or no.
and the code is easily readable:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-swift&quot; data-lang=&quot;swift&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;@IBAction&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;func&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;onActAll&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;sender&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;AnyObject&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ruleThis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;result&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kc&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ruleThis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;showErrors&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Do your segueway or something after success.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You set a trigger for validation, here a button to Next Screen. Then you assign function pointers to the stack os Validations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;override func viewDidLoad() {
    super.viewDidLoad()&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ruleThis.insert(object: textFieldCPF,
    function: checkIfCPFisValid, errorLabel: labelMessageCPF,
    errorMessage: &quot;CPF inválido, sua mensagem personalizada aqui.&quot;)

ruleThis.insert(object: textFieldPassword,
    function: checkIfPasswordIsValid, errorLabel: labelMessagePassword,
    errorMessage: &quot;Sua senha não preenche os resquisitos mínimos de segurança, tente novamente&quot;)

ruleThis.insert(object: textFieldInputCEP,
    function: checkIfCEPisValid, errorLabel: labelMessageCEP,
    errorMessage: &quot;Este CEP não é válido&quot;)

ruleThis.insert(object: segmentedOption,
    function: checkIfIsSelected, errorLabel: labelMessageSegmented,
    errorMessage: &quot;Por favor selecione uma das opções.&quot;) } Then you make a function validation to the object assigned. This coule be simple as
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;func checkIfTextIsBlank(obj: AnyObject?) -&amp;gt; Bool
{
    var result = false&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;if let object = obj as? UITextField {
    if !object.text!.isEmpty { // if is not nil.
        result = true
    }
}

return result } or a little more complex [like this](https://gist.github.com/mulatinho/14546ff8f24eb5b10e01) (a validation check for social number in Brazil), and the results are below:
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[caption id=”attachment_611” align=”alignnone” width=”545”]
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mulatinho.files.wordpress.com/2016/03/rulethis.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://mulatinho.files.wordpress.com/2016/03/rulethis.gif?w=545&quot; alt=&quot;validating screen in iOS with Swift&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; validating screen in iOS with Swift[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me the results are cool and work! I really enjoy work with Swift. :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="iOS" /><category term="programming" /><category term="swift" /><summary type="html">Unfortunately we all know that we can’t put everything what we are working in, on a simple blog, I have to understand this since years ago when I worked at some government department. But I can show what I am doing now just for fun and for registry to me in the future. we were had some problems here, especially when we’d need to try validate a lot of forms that involved things like UITextField, UISegmentedControl, etc. To solve this issue I had to create one class with methods like:.insert(object, checkType, labelError, errorMessage) // magic goes here. .showErrors() // print on screen all erros like below .count() // return the quantity of erros below .result() // return if all tests are passed or no. and the code is easily readable:</summary></entry></feed>